so welcome everyone to uh this week magnets uh as
usual the seminars are recorded and they will be
made public available uh the continued
participation seminar after recording
from beginning it constitutes agreement for the
recording to be disseminated we recommend to mute
your mic and turn off your camera for improving
the the recording and so we have expanded our team
want to welcome anik van der bon and richard
bono as well uh that will be helping with the
with some part technical part and organizing um
so as usual we're gonna have 25 to 30 minutes
presentation uh you can drop questions in
the chat box we can read them afterwards
uh it's an informal um it's informal seminar so
if you need to go don't worry you can catch it
on youtube later um after the seminar gonna
be 15 10 to 15 minutes time for questions
uh you're welcome to to ask them and then there
will be a catch up at the end uh you can you can
stay if you want to catch up with friends
and stuff so uh let me welcome uh jay shah
from mit that's good he's gonna talk about
evidence for an intermittent lunar geodyn dynamo
that is that all right so you can share
your screen jay okay just one second
okay okay fantastic okay great thank you
jay so yeah thank you very much anita and
greg and the whole magnets team for putting
these together uh it's uh one of the positive
uh things of the pandemic that's able to bring
everyone together for these seminars every month
and i'm very appreciative to be a part of it um
my name is jay shaw i'm a postdoc at mit uh in
the department of earth atmosphere and planetary
sciences uh and i'm here to show you some work
from a recent uh paleo intensity experiment
that we did on some apollo regular thresher
to think about the lunar dynamo uh in
collaboration with brannan getzin a former
research research assistant in our group and our
pi ben weiss so let's get to it first i'd like to
just uh dwell upon why we look at the moon in the
first place from a paleomagnetic perspective um
we want to try and understand more about its
interior generally and paleomagnetic data have
helped us to show how it does have
a differentiated interior with its
surface crust with a mantle lying below that
and then uh conducting liquid core lying over
a solid conducting core that has generated these
magnetic fields from itself sustaining dynamo
throughout the history of the moon pretty much and
the data that we have have shown this evidence of
dynamic behavior but they've also given us a
few conundrums and that's largely i believe to
be a limitation of the data that we have itself
given that uh we haven't uh used the most will
obtain the most accurate paleo intensities and
then also kind of have a biased sample selection
trying to seek out that uh dynamo behavior so the
moon is a natural laboratory for dynamo theory and
we believe that there are very complex mechanisms
going on given that there is this high field epoch
at the beginning of the moon history in
the past in that first billion years or so
followed by a two billion year period of a low
field epoch and a cessation of the dynamo so
within the earth's orbit we have the example
of a planetary dynamo that's initiated been
sustained and then ended for us to look at and
we have plenty of samples to look at it with and
first and yeah we just need to get some better
better data to fully understand the complexities
of that dynamo and understand more of what's going
on so let's just start out by having a little bit
of a recap on luna paleomagnetism and what we know
from the data so far um just to take you through
this uh little uh plot of the um time scale of
lunar paleo intensity history that we have uh
based on the data that have been acquired so far
by labs around the world where we have constrained
this initial high field epoch in that first
billion years or so where we have magnetic field
strengths of the range of about 100 microtesters
being recorded um for that first billion years
that uh likely believed to have been driven by a
thermally convective dynamo in the interior uh and
following this um period of high field strength
we have this protracted period of a much lower
field strength dynamo activity where we have
field intensities in the range of about seven
upwards and that goes on for about two billion
years before being capped off by the cessation
of the dynamo which has recently been shown to
have happened about a billion years ago or so
so we have this full history of a dynamo
being initiated sustained and then ended
for us to look at and peace apart and we believe
that there are various mechanisms that could have
driven it for this long period of time that
it has been active for so there's the thermal
convection that may have been driving this initial
high field intensities and then likely to be
some procession going on between the core
and the mantle some mechanical stirring of
that convection to keep it going for up until
about two billion years ago or so where and then
to explain the later more recent field
intensities that have been observed
there may have also been some core crystallization
that further driven the dynamo on the moon but
these mechanisms uh can't quite explain the
intensities that we're seeing so the average
field intensities that we're seeing from
the data can't really be justified by these
mechanisms for generating a dynamic the the
field strengths that they would generate and for
the time periods that would generate from four so
there may well be something missing and that could
be in our sampling which may have been biased
to actually find dynamos so we've been looking
at samples that will have demonstrated remnants
properties that would give us really strong paleo
intensities whilst overlooking samples that
maybe do give much weaker paleo intensities
that could potentially suggest that there's
been intermittence in this dynamo there's a
paper by evans italian 2018 which uh suggested
that dynamo intermittence may well explain how
uh they were specifically looking at the thermal
convective dynamo in that first high field epoch
but potentially how such dynamic field behavior
which based on the lunar energy budget could only
have lasted for such a small period of time could
have been stretched out and conserving that energy
to be dispensed throughout the history of the moon
that may be consistent with also periods of dynamo
inactivity amongst these periods dynamo high field
strength and resulting in a lower average field
than what we've seen with the sample so far so we
may have seen these periods of high field strength
accompanied by the periods of low field strength
which will come out to a lower average field
but we just haven't seen the data that would
justify these periods of low field strength
so these may have been mechanisms
that aren't even that exotic
we have reversals in the earth and
perhaps the moon also underwent such
field reversals and we just haven't required the
data in order to observe this and the accompanying
potentially low period periods of low field
strength amidst the reversals there could be
some secular variation going on in the moon that
we haven't quite observed yet and there could be
some sort of a start stop dynamo mechanism where
the moon was oscillating between having enough the
energy to sustain a dynamo and then falling below
that threshold for dynamo activity they could have
extended the longevity of the dynamo and conserved
work to conserve the energy of the lunar energy
budget so there's actually this paper it's cool
yeah it's cool study um by le pollard ital uh
in 2019 where they took the nrm to susceptibility
ratio of 161 samples from the apollo archives and
worked out a crude approximation to
a paleo intensity for these samples
and they did find a distinctly higher
average field intensity for this high
field epoch in the first billion years for
field activity followed by about two billion
years of a lower average field intensity but
amongst these samples they also found this
regime of high field intensities amidst periods of
well samples which displayed low field intensities
and certainly giving um support to the idea
that we just need to sample more of the rocks in
order to potentially find these examples which
exhibit low field intensity uh recordings so
we need more accurate uh paleo intensity
protocols in order to actually achieve these uh
intensities that we'd like to get and here
i'd like to talk to you about uh controlled
atmosphere thermodynamics demagnetization
which will help us to get to that goal
so controlling the atmosphere
the aim of the game here is to
have the amount of oxygen in your heating
environment such that you're not going to oxidize
your magnetic carriers and you're not going to
reduce your magnetic carriers so the partial
pressure of oxygen we'd like to be in our oven
to be the same as what the samples experienced
in the moon and the literary literature is
actually excellent for outlining what the samples
the oxygen fugacities the oxygen partial pressure
would have been under their formation and trying
to do so under vacuum is far too oxidizing argon
atmospheres also far too oxidizing and doping that
argon atmosphere with hydrogen ends up being
too reducing so we achieve the ideal oxygen
environment by mixing together hydrogen and carbon
dioxide proportions that we can calibrate to be
varying over the range of temperatures as
you're heating the sample to react to form
an equilibrium oxygen composition that will
be of the lunar oxygen fugacity so thereby not
oxidizing and not reducing our magnetic carriers
in our samples and we can actually achieve this
for nearly all planetary samples now by making
our system slightly more reducing or slightly more
oxidizing depending on what the samples would
have liked and just to show you a little plot
that makes this very evident and this is
a lunar basal analog that has been heated
in air and we can see that it demagnetizes
beautifully with the magnetic curie temperature
and if we throw that sample in a controlled
atmosphere we see that we don't sacrifice that
camosite to magnetite we preserve that campsite
magnetization and de-magnetize it with the
curie temperature of camosite retaining that
magnetic remnants record and we've developed a
new system that can actually do this now in
thermal cycling uh in less than 25 minutes
uh which is a factor of four faster than
what we've previously been able to do which
further inhibits uh the chemical alteration of the
samples by having them at high temperatures for
shorter periods of time as well as facilitating a
faster greater sample throughput and making these
experiments way more feasible because
they are time consuming as they are so
now we have the experimental protocol
down in order to continue to um
expand our understanding of this lunar dynamo
throughout time we need to look at more sample
methodologies that can help us to do that so
i'm gonna focus on the apollo regolith fracture
if we go back to that plot by le pollard attal
2019 and you can see that littered throughout the
timeline we have these light blue
points which are the regular thresher
and they are all throughout the apollo timeline
and can help to sample specifically this uh
low field epoch where there's just
so many of these samples so we can
increase our current sparsity of data
by looking at these regular furniture
and just to focus now a bit more on those
i'm going to show you a little schematic on
how they form and why they're excellent magnetic
recorders so why they're actually well suited
to our goals so the regular thresher formed on
the surface of the moon from this lunar soil that
would have been lying on on the surface due to
impacts and just commutation of the materials to
have this but maybe it was basaltic materials
or even relic luna regolith wretched themselves
on the surface of the moon carrying their own
ancient nrm lying within the surface ambient field
of the moon at that time when an impactor came
along and crashed into the surface of the moon
resulting in the heating compaction and
lithification of a new root lunar regular thresher
which has now acquired a new thermal remnant
magnetization in its glassy matrix that is
binding together these clasts which may well have
preserved their own ancient nrm from prior to the
impact or have been re-magnetized to that um
lunar surface field at the time of the impact
with a thermal remnant magnetization and one of
the reasons why these samples are so excellent for
from a paleomagnetic perspective is that this
glassy matrix contains these very fine grained
iron nickel grains that are likely of single
vortex grain size and as such would have
very long relaxation times and capable of
retaining that magnetic field information
for geologic time scales and being ideal for our
analysis so let's look at those samples that um
we're working with here we have a young regular
thresher 60255 and an ancient regular thresher
60019 so i was digging through the uh apollo 16
journal to find why they picked up the sample
that i've spent so long working on in the
first place what what was the guy thinking
and what was his intentions and it
turned out that he he picked it up
because purely because it was the size of half of
a grapefruit and he found that very interesting
as we can hopefully hear if this works in the
little audio uh with him chatting with houston
tony do you read over i sure do charlie
okay did you copy that about this rock
i picked up a half grapefruit size yeah
we sure did it sounds very interesting
very interesting okay and it's
going back 17 okay bag 17.
so yeah very interesting and then um our
ancient regular fracture 60019 um i think
it's a little bigger than half a grapefruit maybe
a full grapefruit here it is on the surface um
and then just another picture after they picked
it up so there's a little before and after
that's all they had for that 601.9 but is his what
i found most remarkable is the just after picking
up these special samples that i've devoted so much
of my life to um captured john young one of the
greatest moments in history where he captured his
co-astronaut charlie duke just after having picked
up 60255 and 601.9 and having to relieve himself
into a crater right next to the lunar module and
sadly or fortunately this uh this moment is
um fairly obscured by the glare of the sun
but they have one of the greatest moments in
history and i just found that quite amusing
so this is our little segment of the half
grapefruit our young ancient uh our young
regular thresher 60255 coming in at about 1.7
billion years old uh and we've sent the sample
uh for our own radiometric dates to get a tighter
constraint on that and you can see that it is um
this dark glassy matrix fine grain matrix with
these white feldspathic clasps amidst that matrix
and here is a picture of
our sample of 6019 our ancient regular thresher
coming in at about 3.3 billion years old
and again we've sent this for our in radiometric
dates to get the tighter constraint on that
and again it is this fine-grained glassy
matrix with these white feldspatic clusts
and getting to the data itself uh i just want to
show you initially the yeah the zydefelt plot from
our young regular thread share 60255 which uh you
can see this low temperature component coming off
and then it just is completely lost to noise
and not really anything that looks beautiful
in any way uh which is kind of the behavior oh
well as in with regards to the high temperature
component there's not really anything that we
can see of a distinct component and this is kind
of the behavior of all of our samples from 605.55
where there's not really a strong high temperature
component there's not much unidirectionality
and there are very large mad angles so there's
not really much of a component there in the high
temperature which is consistent with we're finding
a zero field paleo intensity having been recorded
by the matrix from 60255 uh where our arrive plot
in the high temperature portion has a plateau
that is of zero field and i just want to draw
attention to the scale on the y-axis and the
x-axis where you can see that it's about two
orders of magnitude lower on the y axis so all
these perturbations we can see are actually very
small in relation to how much ptrm it's gaining
and if we stretch that out onto the same axis
uh it's just this one long flat line corresponding
to a zero paleon density now if we do the same
for 6019 our ancient regular thresher again we
can see this low temperature component coming off
and then in the high temperatures we're
not really seeing anything uh which we see
amongst all of our samples from 6w19 matrix uh
with large mad angles and not really much of a
consistent direction again this we're
finding to be consistent with a zero field
early intensity being recorded by this ancient
regular thresher again the y-axis is much
smaller than the x-axis so it's gaining
a ton of ptrm with not much nrm to lose
so just putting this into the context of
the rest of the data that we have so far
you can see that we have these new regular
thresher that plot within error being
a zero field paleo intensity in that low field
epoch where we're expecting to see these middling
field intensities that would be respective of a
procession-driven dynamo or core crystallization
just adding to this um a couple of paleo
intensities of some regular pressure that
are from gazaca his soon to be published work from
the high field epoch and from the low field epoch
where he is finding paleo intensities using
a controlled atmosphere system and so he a
thermal paleo intensity so we're not just finding
a ton of zero field paleo intensities certainly
and what it does seem to be is that we have
possibly found first evidence of intermittence
of the dynamo so these periods where we're
expecting fine field intensities we're finding
very low field pale intensity suggesting
that perhaps the average field
of these epochs may be much lower and there may
be some more complex but not necessarily so exotic
mechanisms going on with regards to luna
dynamo that we should explore further
so yeah just in conclusion i feel like we're
getting closer to understanding the history of
lunardano but there's a ton more work to be
done to fill out the sparse record that we
have so far from the data which i think oxygen
fugacity controlled uh telepathy intensities
will help us significantly to do so as well as
looking at the regular thresher of which there
are so many especially in the low field epoch
and we now have the first telepara intensities
that support an intermittent lunar dynamo
which i feel we should explore further and
before i close out i wanted to give a little
teaser for something else that we found in this
study that we're still working on still trying
to figure out fully uh so we got a class from the
sample and sub sampled this class this is our
young regular stretcher from 1.7 billion years ago
and the class itself is showing a paleo
intensity as well as some unidirectionality
amongst its high temperature component
and it's a nonzero appeal intensity and
we're trying to explore this it may well be
i'm very excited by the prospect of being but
i don't know i'm uh keeping some caution there
that it has actually retained an ancient nrm
from prior to the formation of the regolith
which would be really cool but we've sent out
the sample of the class 4 dating to see if that
fits that theory at all as well as trying to
look at the magnetic mineralogy
within the clast a little further to
see how how reliable recorders they are as well
as looking at the magnetic analogy of the the rest
of the materials we've been looking at to verify
how how great the recorder they are so that that
is yet to be done but on the horizon hopefully
and yeah that's all leave it there for questions
thank you very much well thank you very
much let's give jay big round of applause
and uh we are open for questions uh there
was a question uh from lisa um asking
how many of the high field samples were not
subjected to high fields on sample return any
how many of the high field samples
were not subjected to high fields
is that during time during yeah so during the
mission kind of thing i think so maybe lisa cannon
yeah yourself so just um that high field
seemed to be associated with samples
that had been subjected to a moderate field
in the air in the spaceship on the way home
and i'm just wondering if any of the samples
have not been that's a good question i guess
i mean i'm not really sure about the fields that
they experienced amongst different missions and
that kind of thing but we're seeing low
fields from samples that are obtained from
the same missions okay well that's good so
i think that would potentially suggest that
it's not like a you know blanket they've
all been zapped on apollo 11 kind of thing
maybe i i don't know that's a that's a
good thing to explore though certainly i
yeah i would never want to
rule out contamination but
i think uh because all the ones
we looked at that was what it was
they were irms and it was there was no high field
once you've given it an irm you can't recover it
yeah of course well i mean
even a small iron you just
that's interesting and
worrying at the same time yeah
lisa do you have other questions or i see wind as
a rice hen yeah winner hi jay interesting talk um
i i'm probably going to expose my ignorance
yet again but i just think of the samples
you say that they were there's a trm captured
by the the this um conglomerate the regolith
but is any evidence of any post trm uh shock you
know obviously a lot of meteor impacts on the
surface of the moon and if there's any possibility
of any demagnetization occurring from uh impacts
or can you can you see any clues of any
evidence of um you know because it doesn't
shouldn't really take a huge amount of impact
to magnetize uh well i'm not sure about cameras
of these classes themselves yeah i mean the
class sample i i it's kind of like a far-fetched
idea that i i think i'm kind of holding on to and
thinking is really cool and i mean ben is way more
skeptical than i am on this and i think i'm just
very hopeful so i mean certainly it could have
been somewhat demagnetized but if it has been
that it's not been completely demagnetized at
least i mean it's still recording about 10 micro
tesla field so that i think the the significant
thing at least is the fact that it has recorded a
field from a period of time and if it's been able
to retain that even going through shock then it's
potentially been exposed to an even higher field
from like its original remnants was from a higher
field potentially okay i was also nice to see
you know these uh your your trm curves you don't
see many trm curves that haven't just completely
chemically altered from these lunar materials
and i was very happy to see that they do actually
seem to agree with the predictions of uh nagi
ital's paper from a couple of years ago yeah
that's something we're always bearing
in mind like around that 400 uh
celsius everything seems to be held in uh within
about 200 centigrade of the of the curing point
right all the remnants used to be held in there
or the demonetization curves see that that was
mostly responsible so that was good anyway
enjoyed your talk very nice thanks thank you
uh we have two raised hands so greg was first
and then nick greg do you want to go hi joey um
that was a really really interesting talk
um because my question is kind of this um
prelim result on the 10 micro test i
mean have you actually thought about
also the cooling rate corrections and what
they would do to the result because i mean
you're heating from room temperature to 700 and
back again um in you said was it 25 minutes and
that's that's like a that's a a one degree per
second um temperature change without any hold time
i mean you know how how much in thermal
equilibrium are the samples getting to
at high temperatures and what kind of cooling
rates then does that have for your experiments
because that's going to potentially crank up
your intensity volumes quite substantially
would wait so would having a
longer whole time help us with that
essentially i guess you have to
think about the size of your sample
because once the oven reaches temperature your
sample is lagging behind a little bit it needs
to reach the thermal equilibrium with with the
furnace um but also just the fact that that
you know even if you just heat it straight up
and then cool back down again the the the rate
of temperature change the cooling rate is pretty
huge um and that would um that would mean that the
um cooling rate process the the the um acquisition
of trm the lab is going to be very different
to that acquired in nature that'll have a
big impact on your paleo intensity results
okay yeah that's something to think about yeah no
definitely something to think about uh i mean yeah
with regards to just to clarify more on the
experiment uh heating rates and cooling rates uh
it heats up in about i would say uh 15 minutes
or so and then we have a whole time of about
five minutes at temperature and we have a
thermocouple right next to the samples as well to
check that the sample temperature within the
controlled atmosphere tube is actually the
temperature of what the oven is reading because
they're normally fairly different um so we go by
the sample temperature within the atmosphere tube
and we cool down in about five minutes i'd say
so yeah i'll i'll think about that
thanks greg yeah it's a good point
that cooling rate the comparison
between experiments and
nature it's really good question uh to investigate
so we have nick with your hand is right yeah
sure thanks thanks for the talk jay we've been
watching your talk as a as a family over breakfast
here in california and my nine-year-old maddie
has a has a question for you oh really um it's
really cool that you handle the moon rocks but do
you always have to use gloves or are you sometimes
allowed to use your bare hands we have to use
gloves i have to be very responsible when i'm
working with this as much as there is temptation
to actually touch the moon rock myself
i do refrain i wish i could be so lucky and
why do you have to wear gloves just to prevent
contamination if they with regards to us i mean
i'm not i'm not very magnetic as i am so i'm not
going to magnetize the rocks with my fingers
uh but if anyone ever wanted to do any studies
uh on the samples after me i'm sure they
don't want my sweaty fingers all over them
okay thank you thank you very much
thank you we always welcome questions from early
career scientists you're the youngest welcome
thank you and we have a question from yes
andrei do you want to ask your question yeah
can you hear me okay jay the ques the question the
question is and it's more it's more like a concern
and i'm wondering why did you uh select uh brexit
uh regulate and pressure and because it's known
from the terrestrial impacts that fracture are
generally not very good recorder of pelleting of
of geomagnetic field and how can you how
can you be sure that it acquires theory
but in particular that you you you absolutely
don't have field controls whether it's
where with respect to the cracker even you don't
have a control which which impact event created
that that particular breakthrough isn't it so
well it's it is my understanding that they were
heated up during the impact itself given that the
radiometric clocks are reset during that impacting
uh so they do they i think they do get heated
up and then cooling down to acquire an etrm
yeah okay so you didn't mention that with
regards to mineralogy they're excellent for
paleomagnetic analysis and they and they have been
behaving very well with our controlled atmosphere
system which is just yeah for us yeah and uh and
in continuation of this did you also try bezels
so i i don't think i have tried a puzzle i might
have um but yeah the issues that we've found with
basalts in the past are that because they have
trolite in them the trollite often will reduce
to iron metal and then release that sulfur so
until we can control sulfur fugacity we can't
prevent the alteration of that line so we see
this big spike in magnetization once we once was
so until we can do that and
also the basalts are from
a pretty discreet time period on that
lunar record so it'd be great to look
at as many pesos as we can but we
can't look at the whole time scale
yeah that's that's understandable thank you very
much yeah great talk thanks andre yeah great work
thank you thank you are there any other questions
space people no we have another race oh no i
think that's well win you have another question
oh you wrote some sorry exact but i was just
curious as to whether jay uh if you've got any uh
grain size estimates of the magnetic carriers
not yet okay that would be interesting to do
uh obviously to look at the um reliable of
the remnants but also for the cooling rate
uh corrections that greg mentioned i think we
could get a better estimate if we if we knew
the distribution of particle sizes you had okay
that's a good point yeah i'm going to make that
priority honestly actually because there's a
lot of yeah magnetic mineralogy rock magnetism
experiments we need to do all my samples and we
just don't have a lot of the instruments in our
lab so it's not the first uh protocol typically
so we're gonna gonna get to the magnetic analogy
as soon as i can yeah great
all right thanks jay thanks
well thank you thank you jay i
think we don't have other questions
do we okay not for now then uh thanks again
jay for giving this very nice talk and
i think we can we can conclude
here the recorded part
cheers
depending on the region you
are are we still recording greg
uh sorry do you want to throw up the last
slides just to let people know what's coming um
oh yeah sure sure ex magnets yay could you please
uh uh stop sharing or okay i can kick you out
right okay so um the next seminar is the 14th of
april we are gonna have andrea bidderman we are
gonna circulate more informations about this
um then we are gonna have a break for the egu
that's gonna last two weeks so you're gonna be
all very busy and you feel up there it's gonna be
a nice break i think and after egu we are gonna
from may we're gonna start uh um having one eu
europe us time and one eastern hemisphere and
time slots so we're going to have speakers from
australia la trobe university where a few lined
up but the problem is still to to to organize and
we always welcome more speakers especially
we encourage early career scientists and
and if you have any suggestions or feedback
or anything you please feel free to contact
me or greg by email or via our
social media so thank you very much